Finding Aid for Helen M. Atwell Papers 1965-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen M. Atwell Papers 1965-1994, 1972-1987
Atwell, Helen M.
2 linear feet
Dearborn, Michigan community volunteer and activist with various Arab-American organizations, including the Southeast Dearborn Community Council and the Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services. The collection includes files relating to her involvement with Arab-American organizations; also collected materials related to the Arab-American community of southeastern Michigan.
02143 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The Helen M. Atwell Collection was donated by Helen M. Atwell (donor number 9227 ) in July 2002.
The collection is open for research.
Helen Mohammed Okdie Atwell was born in 1934 to Mohammed and Fatme Okdie, immigrants from Lebanon living in Dearborn Michigan. Atwell graduated from Fordson High School in 1952, and married John Atwell in 1952. The Atwells had eight children, divorcing in 1972. Atwell received her BA in Urban and Regional Studies from University of Michigan-Dearborn in 1978.
Since the 1960's, Atwell has been an activist and volunteer in her community of Southeast Dearborn. She volunteered at the Southeast Dearborn Community Council (SEDCC), then served as the executive director from 1978 until the organization folded in 1986. Atwell was a key activist in the southeast area's struggle against the City of Dearborn's desire for urban renewal, as well as the author of several federal grants that led to the construction of low-income housing and the redevelopment of the Dix and Vernor business district as the 'Arabian Village'.
Atwell was one of the founders of the Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services (ACCESS), serving as the first treasurer and continually an active board member. Atwell volunteered at the American Muslim Society, which her parents helped establish. Eventually the Mosque split into two factions, and the early Lebanese community left and began a new association called American Bekka Center. Atwell served on the Women's Auxiliary in both organizations, and became the first female board member at the Bekka Center. Atwell now serves as the Bekka Center's first female vice-president.
In addition to Atwell's work at the SEDCC, ACCESS and the Mosques, she was also active in a number of other organizations including the Salina School District PTA, the Arab-American Anti-Discrimination Committee, the Lebanese Club, the Arab American Political Committee, the Arab Democratic Club, and the Arab World Festival.
After leaving the SEDCC in 1986, Atwell joined the staff of State Senator Agnes Dubronski as a Legislative Aid. In 1991 she became the Executive Director of the Metro Detroit Service Station Dealers' Association. In the mid-1990's Atwell joined other family members in running a small business.
Although Atwell is now often busy with her twenty-four grandchildren, she is still active in many organizations, particularly the Bekka Center.
The Helen M. Atwell collection (1965-1994) contains information on Atwell, a community activist and volunteer in Southeast Dearborn. Atwell was involved with numerous organizations. A majority of the records are about Atwell's work with the Southeast Dearborn Community Council, SEDCC. Also included are materials related to her involvement with the Salina PTA, the Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services, ACCESS, and other Arab-American organizations, as well as a limited amount of her personal papers. The collection is a record of activism in the neighborhood of Southeast Dearborn and the Arab-American community. Researchers interested in immigrant communities, Arab-Americans and urban neighborhood renewal should find material of interest.
Subjects:
Atwell, Helen M.; Arab Americans--Michigan--Dearborn.; Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.; Dearborn (Mich.); Southeast Dearborn Community Council.
- Personal Papers 1972-1991
  The Personal Papers series includes Atwell's biographical information, her correspondence, including negative anonymous correspondence in regard to her efforts for the Arab-American community, presentations and speeches given about her culture to a variety of audiences, a notebook with information on activities from the early 1970's, information on her campaign for city council in 1973, and collected clippings on Atwell.
  - Biographical circa 1976-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1976-1987, undated (Box 1)
  - Presentations and Speeches 1973-1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Notebook circa 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Atwell's Campaign for City Council 1973 (Box 1)
  - Campaign Clippings 1973 (Box 1)
  - Clippings on Atwell 1973-1981, undated (Box 1)
- Activities 1969-1994
  The Activities series consists of information on the Salina Schools, ACCESS, and other Arab-American organizations. Materials relating to the Salina schools include PTA meetings, a lawsuit against the Dearborn School District, and information on bilingual education in the area. The ACCESS materials include a commentary on board members written in 1975 by Ishmail Ahmed, the current executive director of ACCESS, a publication on Arab-American Families for social service providers, and clippings. The Arab-American organizations records consists of information on the following organizations: the Arab Arab-American Council of Dearborn, the Feminist Arab-American Network, the Metro Detroit Service Association Inc., an Affiliation of Arab American Service Station Owners, and general pamphlets and clippings about the Arab-American community.
  - Schools 1969-1990
    - Salina Parent Teacher Association (PTA) 1969-1973, undated (Box 1)
    - Dearborn School District vs. Taxpayers, Dearborn Federation of Teachers, Lawsuit regarding School Millages 1975 (Box 1)
    - Dearborn School Census 1978 (Box 1)
    - Effects of Native Language Development on Students Second Language Achievement (Dissertation on Bilingual Education in Dearborn) by Wageh Saad 1990 (Box 1)
  - Arab Community Center for Economics and Social Services (ACCESS) 1975-1991
    - General, Information on the Board and Executive Committee by Ishmail Ahmed 1975, 1983, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Arab American Families: A Resource Manual for Human Service Providers 1988 (Box 1)
    - ACCESS News Clippings 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Arab-American Organizations 1974-1994
    - Arab-American Council of Dearborn 1985 (Box 1)
    - Feminist Arab-American Network 1980-1983 (Box 1)
    - Metro Detroit Service Association Inc. an Affiliation of Arab American Service Station Owners 1994 (Box 1)
    - Arab Americans, General Pamphlets 1974-1981 (Box 1)
    - Arab American Community News Clippings 1978-1986 (Box 1)
- Southeast Dearborn Community Council (SEDCC) 1965-1987
  The Southeast Dearborn Community Council (SEDCC) series contains a great deal of information on both the organization and the Southeast Dearborn neighborhood from the early 1970's until the organization folded in 1986. The materials consist of legal documents, flyers, newsletters, general pamphlets, and background research; neighborhood information includes correspondence, efforts against the city of Dearborn on urban renewal plans. Additional information includes surveys and reports on the Arab-American community and available social services, records on the purchase and selling of homes and lots in the area by the City of Dearborn, grant applications to several agencies, and news clippings about the neighborhood and community. Additional information on the SEDCC can be found in the Personal Papers series, particularly in Atwell's notebook.
  - Organizational 1970-1986
    - Incorporation and Legal Documents 1974-1990 (Box 1)
    - General 1981-1986 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters and Flyers 1970-1986 (Box 1)
    - Wayne County Neighborhood Legal Services Board 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Legal Assistance file circa 1986 (Box 1)
    - Collected Research on Arab Americans and Urban Renewal 1978, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
    - Petition to Stop the Closure of SEDCC 1986 (Box 1)
  - Neighborhood Information 1965-1985
    - General Neighborhood Information 1965-1980 (Box 1)
    - Dearborn Capital Improvement Planning Program 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - Edward C. Levy Co. 1971-1977 (Box 1)
    - Maps and Zoning Information 1978-1979, undated (Box 1)
    - Dearborn History Information 1979-1982 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1971-1985 (Box 1)
  - Surveys and Reports
    - Community Background Survey by Laura D. Wigle 1970 (Box 1)
    - Community Survey and Petition by SEDCC 1971 (Box 1)
    - Community Survey Results by Aswad 1971 (Box 1)
    - The South East Dearborn Arab Community Struggles for Survival, Barbara C. Aswad circa 1974 (Box 1)
    - Community Health and Social Services Survey 1979 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire on SEDCC 1978 (Box 2)
    - Community Public Opinion Survey 1978 (Box 2)
    - The Process of Change in a Community Organization: An Anthropological analysis of an Urban System (on SEDCC), by Richard D. Robinson 1984 (Box 2)
    - A Study of the Middle East Community in the Detroit Metro Area by the United Community Services of Metropolitan Detroit 1986 (Box 2)
  - Housing
    - Tenant's Rights circa 1972 (Box 2)
    - Lot and House Purchases 1974-1980 (Box 2)
    - City of Dearborn Housing Survey Forms 1977 (Box 2)
    - Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Discrimination Complaint Forms 1978 (Box 2)
    - New Housing Proposal: Soil Investigation 1978 (Box 2)
    - Demolitions 1978 (Box 2)
  - Funding
    - HUD Neighborhood Self-Help Program Grant Application 1980 (Box 2)
    - Mobil Oil Grant 1983 (Box 2)
    - Dearborn Block Grant Applications 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - Clippings
    - Collected News Clippings 1970-1987 (Box 2)